to convert methane, you actually have to dissociate methane to methyl radical and hydrogen radical
and the small and the sort of the sacronium aids are really good at doing that because
they have a place for the hydrogen and have a place for the methyl group.
And so they actually convert rather quickly to a carbide and as such actually when they
oxidize, they only oxidize on the outside.
While the smaller species actually oxidize pretty much an oxide in the middle and maybe
later down the lines in there pretty hot, they may grab some carbon.
You get the very early days.
It makes sense to me, but we don't have the experimental evidence that it works.
That's a game that works really well.
So it may get some interesting surprises there.
Yeah, I think that would be helpful for us because if we learn, for instance, I'm not
saying this is the case, but we learn that it's unlikely that we're converting boron
carbide to, or that we're oxidizing the boron carbides.
Let's put it that way.
Then that probably tells us we're making the oxide on the way to the boron carbide instead
of intercepting it.
And that'll help us think through what kind of experiments we might want to run to measure
this.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, now what could then be a good way to...
So let's get back to the basics for a second then.
So this is something where you start with your polymer precursors.
Okay.
So that's pretty much the sort of the long chain, hard to carbon with kind of a boron
side chain type sort of stuff.
Okay.
And then I guess the question is to some extent, so we could do a series of simulations where
we could start with the precursor clearly.
That's kind of trivial, but it's a nice place to start.
And that we can just do sort of partial conversions to the boron carbide and just run the simulation
and just stop it at, let's say, 10 different stages.
Yeah.
Mix it with oxygen and kind of see how that evolves.
I mean, that's a pretty nice simulation to do.
Yeah.
And then see what we get.
I mean, that's...
Yeah, I would imagine that the initial decaborane would probably...
You don't want...
I would imagine that these would be extremely oxygen sensitive.
Yeah.
I think that...
I don't even know how Rob's group handles these things.
Yeah.
When it's not in the polymer, it's pyrophoric.
Okay.
But in the polymer, for whatever reason, I don't know if it's that it's diffusion of
the oxygen is slow or wet.
But yeah.
So one could imagine that if there's any oxygen around right when you lose the hydrogens,
if you don't immediately make water, then maybe, yeah, you just go nuts oxidizing everything.
Yeah.
That's a nice simulation through.
Cool.
Now, we have some practical issues in my group that everybody is...
Let's see.
Everybody is either seven months pregnant or extremely busy at this moment in time.
So you have to kind of time this a little bit.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, yeah, for practical reasons, Joepjeet would be the best person to do this right now.
But I had to fund them out of a different project for this semester that he has to at
least show some results for before he can go back to...
I mean, he keeps doing his muhri stuff.
That's fine.
But we have to put another sort of muhri task on his desk at this point in time.
Yeah.
Let's just talk about time scale for this.
And when you would like this idea to happen, I'm not sure if there's any sort of big hurry
for you in any of this stuff.
For me personally, and you, you're Anthony, you can speak up.
I don't think there's a huge hurry because, you know, this was more...
We had this question of like, would it ever be possible to do this in air?
Right?
Yeah.
And so we tried it, it didn't work.
And now the question is why?
And if we understood why, could we then design conditions that would let us do it?
And so that's sort of like, I don't know, kind of a pie in the sky thing.
You know, it would be amazing if you could just start making carbides in open air.
Yep.
But it's unlikely to really happen.
So yeah, I'm not too, I'm not too bothered about waiting, but I don't know, again, if
Anthony or Yuki have different thoughts.
Well, I don't really mind about time.
Okay.
How about the following then?
Let's, let's get this semester with all this craziness out of the way.
And then maybe, maybe start something serious on this thing.
Would that be okay?
Sure.
Great.
So, I have to see what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what, what,
what is this.
I think Jor-Piet would be a good person to do this, but Mahmoud could do it as well.
It depends a bit how it's, I mean, he's really getting some really nice stuff out of the
Zirconian carbide stuff.
So I want him to spend as much time as he can to get JP's attention, which is hard.
Yeah.
But yeah.
But this, I like this.
I like the idea.
So just, at least from our perspective, it's really clean because we have all the input
structures.
Now our force filters may be not the greatest for the boron-oxidant carbide.
I'm not, I'm not even sure what that boron-oxidant carbon phase diagram even looks like.
Any idea if there are some weird things in there?
I think Yuki would know the most about this.
Yeah.
But yeah.
But the final boron carbide that you get, I guess you can probably leave it in air and
it will still be roughly a boron carbide for a long period of time.
Yeah.
It should probably maybe oxidize a little bit on the surface, but nothing dramatic changes
in its properties.
Is that, is that right?
I mean, like, yeah, I'm sorry.
I didn't get your point.
Now, in the end, you make a boron carbide.
Yeah.
And the boron carbide itself is relatively inert towards oxygen.
I mean, it should be because it's, it's, what is it?
It's pretty much graphite with a little bit of boron in it.
Mm-hmm.
It's B, it's, what is it?
It's B, B-C4 or B4C13 or that sort of stuff?
B4C.
Oh, well, well, it's mainly like, it's not like pure, it's not like pure B4C.
It's actually like B4, it's like B12C3-ish.
Oh, so it's actually rich in boron and poor in carbon.
Sorry.
Yeah, it's just a long way around.
So is that, is that structure actually stable in oxygen?
I mean, it's stable enough that we can't, we make it hand sampled up, you know.
Okay.
But I mean, I worked for a long time in the Maxine field, which is pretty much, you
know, titanium carbide stuff.
And there that, that field had a problem that you couldn't actually leave a Maxine for two
months.
You could synthesize it.
Two months later, it would pretty much be rutile and graphite.
Yeah, okay.
I was curious, I could imagine that thermonetically, I would imagine that B203 and graphite, really
more stable.
They were enhanced down compared to B4C.
I mean, I cannot imagine anything else.
But that doesn't mean it happens because it's all kinetics essentially.
But I would imagine if you have a lump of pure boron and you leave it on your desk, it's
probably not going to be pure boron again after a month.
Is that, is that fair?
I think that's fair.
I mean, I guess we haven't, I have not written anything about the lifetime.
And I don't know if we've gone out of our way to study the stability of what we make
yet.
Yeah.
It's all about how well the oxide is.
I would imagine that your, whatever it is, your surface will probably oxidize in some
way or form.
But if it makes a nice, stable, high density oxide, then no, the rest of the material doesn't
care.
Yeah, yeah.
That's actually, in itself, interesting.
I had no idea if you have a, when boron clearly is actually a pretty stable material from
cohesive energy perspective, but I just don't know what it does.
Can you, I sure miss you make a fine powder of it.
It's clear what it's going to do.
But if you have a, if a big chunk of it, I don't know if it's, if it actually is relatively
stable.
Yeah.
I could imagine it might be.
The big deal, the problem with boron is that it's oxides actually have a relatively high
vapor pressure.
So you cannot take it to high temperature because they evaporate off and they just keep oxidizing.
But at low temperature, that's not such a big deal, I would imagine.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I mean, there's been some work and I think Yuki looked this up for her talk where people
were converting between different phases and that's sort of what got her started on this.
But yeah, I think at this point, all we know is we, if we do this in air, we end with basically
boronic acid.
Okay.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Borica.
Yeah.
And we don't know what happens in between.
But you know, this is maybe what you'd expect is sort of the thermodynamic endpoint and
it is what we find.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
Here, I think she found the element according to AI.
Elemental boron is generally stable in air at room temperature.
So there you go.
But that can't see.
If you go high temperature, then indeed it will walk away towards all sort of stuff.
Yeah.
And I would imagine that the boron carbides will probably do the same thing because they
are pretty much very boron rich.
They might be a little bit less, more resistive than pure boron, but I think you'll probably
see kind of the same thing.
And clearly if you go high temperature, then yeah, any beta-free and boron acid pretty
much take over because they'll just evaporate off.
Yeah.
Stable in air at room temperature, forming a thin protective layer of boron oxide or
hydroxide that inhibits further corrosion.
Okay.
That makes sense.
So that's kind of interesting.
So that means that somewhere in your, since you say that if you do this in air that you're
pretty much, I guess that means that clearly your temperature is high enough and I would
imagine it gets pretty hot in there that you cannot make a protective oxide anymore and
pretty much the beta-free prefers to be in vapor phase and that's in general the problem
with boron oxide.
Yeah.
So that's sort of very stable oxide intermediates.
So that's why also, I mean, in the high energy material, they never really use boron, even
though they would love to use it.
They use aluminium instead because boron has all those sort of relatively stable low molecular
rate intermediates that just evaporates off and you never actually can get complete combustion
of boron.
Because all those intermediates are so stable and they evaporate off so you never actually
get to beta-free.
You end up with HOBO if I remember correctly.
Okay.
Interesting.
I used to work on high explosives a long time ago and there was indeed, I mean people just
looked at heat information and say, oh, boron should be the best thing around.
It's the lightest and atomic weight is a big deal in that community because if you launch
a rocket, the weight of your fuel is a big deal.
So boron looks beautiful but you can, and also beta-free is a great, great endpoint.
Yeah, thermally, but you never get to beta-free.
Yeah.
Because there's too many intermediates that just get made, fly off and you never get actually
a full energy out of it.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't know if we ever, so if that were the case, I mean, we only tried this once
and then we looked at the solid that was left behind but I guess it's conceivable that these
like volatile things at high temperature would condense and so if we had something around
that we could try to condense them on, we could look for them.
Yeah.
So that would be another, I mean this would probably, we wouldn't do it right away but
this would be informed by sort of the simulations you have, right?
If you're bringing things like this that we could try to collect.
Yeah, that actually makes it interesting because there are lots of interesting kinetics in
there.
Yeah.
I mean, from your perspective, I guess it would be a success if you actually have a
material that has even if an oxide surface still is kind of a nice carbide in the subsurface.
Yeah.
When you handle the material well enough, can you make it cool down fast enough in some
way or form that you avoid complete evaporation of the oxide?
Yeah.
Yep.
Yeah, I think anything, you know, we, well, so I think yeah, there's two possible outcomes
of this, right?
One is we learn how to make some kind of carbide in any amount under atmospheric O2.
That would be cool.
Or we learn why it doesn't work.
Both of those are totally fine.
Yeah.
I would imagine that if you have really good thermal contact that you may be able to take
temperature around quick enough that you can avoid oxidizing products to disappear on
you.
But you may have to have to have sort of a nice thin layer of a really good sort of
thermal contact, some sort of metal or some description or some along those lines.
Yeah.
It could be.
Okay.
That's not interesting.
So yeah, let's get back to, I'll keep this one in mind so I don't overload my group members
for May.
I won't talk about it because they'll get too stressed out.
Well, I think this sounds pretty interesting.
It gives us a nice sort of, I mean, you can do a really nice study on just, you know,
boron, carbon, oxygen species as sort of a, you know, 10 to 20 atom scale.
You can do a lot of nice quantum chemistry on those type of things and get actually a
very accurate force field for those type of kinetics.
Cool.
Cool, cool, cool.
Sounds good.
Okay.
So we go that way then.
I don't know if there's anything else.
No, from my side.
So let's see, we have a sort of a Murie meeting somewhere this week.
I got my, I know that Rob moves things around and figured that one of you probably knows
this is, oh, we have a complete Murie two hour type sort of thing right now.
So I got a Murie meeting for noon on Wednesday and one for, and one at one o'clock on Wednesday.
That's how you see it on your calendar then?
But I think the one on the right.
Oh, okay.
But that, that, that, that constellation hasn't been formally announced yet.
Okay.
So I knew our, our estimate is that the one at noon will happen at about one o'clock
vote.
That's correct.
Okay.
Well, let's see how that goes.
Yeah.
I'm sure Rob will confirm all these things to us.
Probably well before, well before Wednesday morning.
Yeah, let's hope.
Okay.
Well, I'll probably see you in some way or form then on Wednesday.
Sounds good.
Okay.
See you all.
Oh, so Wednesday I asked Mosh there to present.
So what she does actually is, it's not completely relevant, but it has some interest.
So she's been working, she works on my other Murie, but she's pretty much burning titanium
boron particles.
And that's actually pretty fascinating.
So it's not exactly what we're talking about.
We had lots of similarities.
It's pretty much about the competition between titanium burning and boron burning.
Titanium makes a really nice oxide, as we all know.
And boron at the temperature we operate out makes a really crappy oxide.
Okay.
But the titanium burns faster than boron.
So if it direct competition between if oxygen, if you're titanium boron gets exposed to oxygen,
first the titanium grabs the oxygen and later the boron can access to the thing.
So you get really, I mean, experiment, they actually get very interesting almost microscope
features.
So they make kind of a molten titanium oxide.
I mean, this is hot.
This is now 3000 Kelvin or so.
So they make a molten titanium oxide.
And then every time they get a sort of a big volcanic eruption when a whole bunch of boron
oxide kind of, and that's pretty boron oxide at that page well into the gas species, because
it makes it way through that liquid titanium oxide.
So we've been doing some simulations.
He didn't doesn't see the volcanoes, but we see enough things that kind of show similar
chemistry.
Yeah, that's cool.
Yep.
What's the, I guess, though, these like, maybe, maybe volcano-y things, then you see experimentally,
what's the, what's the like spacing between them?
The spacing between, you mean the size of the volcanoes?
Or just like, I'm assuming that like, you know, there must be some information about
like the distance between them, since you have this like mass transport, right?
Yeah, I don't know.
I already see the pretty pictures.
We have, we talked with them.
This is a, I don't know if you know, this is Scott's, I always get a surname, but give
me a second.
So we're working in Aldermury with Scott, Scott, Scott, Scott McCormack.
He does really high temperature experiments on all these sort of boron carbides, zirconium
boride, silicon carbides, and that sort of stuff.
He really moved from UC Davis to UC Berkeley, I think, or something along those lines.
His experiments are pretty nice and we can, and it's also a nice temperature for our simulations
because at 3000 Kelvin, things go pretty quickly.
So in a couple of nanoseconds we actually can get some meaningful results typically.
Yeah, cool.
Oh yeah, so that might all get presented on Wednesday.
Okay, see you then.
Yeah.
Bye.